Guide to the Mount Vernon Seminary and College collection of biographical materials and correspondence with Marjorie Merriweather Post, 1901-1999 MVC0017.MS
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mount Vernon Seminary and College collection of biographical materials and correspondence with Marjorie Merriweather Post
1901-1999
1937-1973
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mount Vernon College
MVC0017.MS
2.5 Linear Feet 2 document boxes, 2 slim document boxes, 1 flat box.
Marjorie Merriweather Post, Founder of the General Foods Corporation, was the First Alumna Trustee of Mount Vernon Seminary and College. She gave untiringly to Mount Vernon Seminary and College, and maintained a lifelong relationship with the school that kept her in constant communication with George Lloyd and later Peter Pelham, Presidents of Mount Vernon Seminary and College. This collection contains correspondence, photographs, newspaper articles, invitations, speeches and memorabilia, most of which pertain to Post's relationship to Mount Vernon Seminary and College. The material dates between 1901 and 1999, with the bulk of the material dating between 1937 and 1973.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 2 series: Mount Vernon Seminary and College materials, and Biographical materials. While nearly all of the materials in the collection are relevant to Mount Vernon Seminary and College, it became clear that some of the materials were of more general interest for the biographical information they contained, for example the newspaper articles and architectural notes on Hillwood, and thus warranted a separate series.
Biographical / Historical
Marjorie Merriweather Post (1887-1973), founder of the General Foods Corporation and a renowned philanthropist, was the first alumna trustee of Mount Vernon Seminary and College, and one of its largest donors. In 1999 the Mount Vernon campus and legacy became part of the George Washington University.
Mrs. Post was born in Springfield Illinois, on March 5, 1887, but spent most of her childhood in Battle Creek, Michigan. She was the only child of C.W. Post, who founded the Postum Cereal Company and invented its flagship product, Postum, a nutritious coffee substitute beverage. She attended public school in Battle Creek and graduated from Mount Vernon Seminary at age 17. She inherited her father's business at age 27, but later expanded her fortune enormously by adding frozen foods to her company's repertoire, renaming the business General Foods. She became known as one of the wealthiest people in the United States, with a fortune worth an estimated $100-250 million, and was especially known for her generosity. This included financing a 2,000 bed field hospital in France during the First World War, and providing hot meals during the Great Depression through the Salvation Army. Her estates were legendary, including Hillwood, which now operates as a museum under the Smithsonian Institution and houses her unique collection of Russian Imperial art, and Mar-a-Lago in Palm Beach, which she gave to the United States Government to use as a VIP retreat for visiting dignitaries. She married four times, to Edward B. Close, Edward F. Hutton, Joseph P. Davies, and Herbert A. May. She restored her maiden name after her divorce with Mr. May. She had three daughters, Eleanor and Adelaide by Edward Close, and Nedenia Marjorie Hutton, by Edward Hutton. All three daughters attended Mount Vernon Seminary, as well as two of her granddaughters. She gave untiringly to Mount Vernon Seminary and College, in outright gifts and by financing construction on the Foxhall Road campus including Post Hall, named for her parents, and Merriweather Hall.
She died at age 86 at Hillwood.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence from Marjorie Merriweather Post to administrators of Mount Vernon Seminary and College, as well as biographical information collected about Marjorie Merriweather Post, such a snewspaper articles, photographs, slides, negatives, obituaries, Mount Vernon College Bulletins, playbills, a metal sign and a hand-bound book that document the lifelong relationship that Marjorie Merriweather Post maintained with Mount Vernon Seminary and College as the first Alumna Trustee and Honorary Chairman of the Board of Trustees. The bulk of the material dates from 1937 to 1973. The inclusive dates are 1901 to 1999. In addition to being the first Alumna Trustee and Honorary Chairman of the board, Mrs. Post was also one of the largest donors to Mount Vernon and was in nearly constant communication with the President of the school. Much of the correspondence is concerned with gifts made by Mrs. Post to Mount Vernon, and the construction of Post Hall, which Mrs. Post financed in honor of her parents. The correspondence illustrates how important Mrs. Post was to Mount Vernon and the influence that she held there. The newspaper and magazine articles are primarily concerned with Mrs. Post's lifestyle, especially her extraordinary estates, Hillwood and Mar-a-Lago. Most of the photographs depict the dedication of Post Hall and the 92nd Founder's Day celebration at which Mrs. Post was honored with a speech.
Related Materials
Marjorie Merriweather Post's personal papers are held by the Bentley Historical Library at the University of Michigan as part of the Post Family papers.
Women -- History; Photographs; Correspondence; Education; Washington (D.C.); Education, Higher -- United States; Architecture -- Washington (D.C.); May, Herbert A.; May, Herbert A., Jr.; Post, Marjorie Merriweather; Pelham, Peter; Lloyd, George; Mount Vernon Seminary; Mount Vernon College
- Mount Vernon Seminary and College materials, 1901-1999; Series 1
  Arrangement
  Series 1, Mount Vernon Seminary and College Materials, is organized into two sub-series: Documents and memorabilia and Photographs. Correspondence in Sub-series 1 has been arranged in chronological order. All other documents are in the order they were received, with the exception of over-size material which has been boxed separately.
  Scope and Contents
  This series comprises two sub-series: documents and memorabilia, and photographs.
  The documents are primarily correspondence between Mrs. Post and the President of Mount Vernon College, George Lloyd and later Peter Pelham, or between Mrs. Post's secretaries or Clyde Ault, her business manager, and the President. The bulk of the material dates from 1937 to 1978. Also included in this sub-series is correspondence of Herbert A. May, her fourth husband, and his son Herbert A. May Jr., concerning business of the Board of Trustees. In addition to the correspondence are a hand bound copy of the speech delivered in honor of Mrs. Post at the 92nd Founder's Day celebration in 1966, a metal sign that reads "Marjorie Merriweather Post First Alumna Trustee 1933" and an address delivered in her honor at the dedication of Post Hall, which Mrs. Post financed as a memorial to her parents. This series also contains obituaries and correspondence regarding Mount Vernon's reactions to Mrs. Post's death.
  The photographs date from 1935-1966. Of note are the photographs taken at the Post Hall dedication and the 92nd Founder's Day celebration. Also there is at least one photograph that was taken on a roof at the 1100 M St. NW campus, featuring Mrs. Post in a "Turkish Woman" costume circa 1904-1917.
  - Documents and memorabilia, 1901-1993; 1937-1973; Series 1, sub-series 1
    - Correspondence and documents, 1955-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1937-1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1953-1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Corespondence, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence and documents, 1970-1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Herbert A. May Sr. correspondence and documents, 1958-1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Herbert A. May Jr. correspondence, 1962-1969 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Nedenia Marjorie Hutton correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - MVC Bulletins, 1957-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Fundraising records and correspondence, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Post Hall materials, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Founder's Day convocation, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Metal sign: First Alumna Trustee, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Obituaries and memorial materials, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Biographical materials and playbills, 1901-1993 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, 1904-1970; 1950-1970; Series 1, sub-series 2
    - Founder's Day photographs, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Photographs, 1935-1966 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Slides, 1954-1958 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Negatives, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Photographs -- Oversize, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Biographical materials, 1967-1999; 1967-1973; Series 2
  All folders are arranged in the order they were received.
  Series 2 contains newspaper articles, architectural notes on Hillwood, and an Issue of Life magazine featuring her daughter Dina Merrill and Hillwood. The materials date from 1901 to 1999. The newspaper articles are mainly concerned with Mrs. Post's estates, her yacht the Sea Cloud, and her philanthropic work. The notes on Hillwood were prepared for the American Institute of Architects' tour through the property, and describe in detail the house and the remarkable art collection. There are also articles about Mar-a-Lago, her winter residence in Palm Beach, with extensive photographs of the interior. The newspaper articles also provide some personal details about Mrs. Post beyond the opulence of her lifestyle, significantly regarding her generosity and good will toward her staff.
  - Hillwood notes, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper articles, 1966-1972 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper articles, 1960-1996 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper articles, 1970-1999 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Life Magazine, 1960 January 11 (Box 5, Folder 2)